{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Titu mir's movement considered one of the Muslim reform movement mainly aimed at eradicating which of the following systems?",
            "optionA": "  Polygamy ",
            "optionB": "  Against Hindu landlords and British indigo planters ",
            "optionC": "  Easy divorce ",
            "optionD": "  Working against Indian national movement ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTitu mir's movement- It was same as wahabi movement. It turned Muslim peasants into militant against Hindu landlords and British indigo planters. Titu mir's movement considered one of the Muslim reform movement mainly aimed at eradicating against Hindu landlords and British indigo planters. ",
            "keyString": "684549s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The \"Arya Samaj\" was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Swami Dayananda Saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionC": "  Keshav Chandra Sen ",
            "optionD": "  Ishwar Chandra VidyaSagar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Swami Dayanand Saraswati founded Arya samaj (1875) in Mumbai. Members of Arya Samaj believed in one God but rejected the worship of idols. The motto of Arya samaj is - Make The World Great. The samaj is associated with the society named \"Dayanand Anglo Vedic (DAV)\".",
            "keyString": "684656s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dayananda was born on February 12 in 1824, in the town of Tankara, near Morvi (Morbi) in the Kathiawar region of the princely state of__________",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDayanand Saraswati was born in the village of Tankara, near Morvi (Morbi) in the Kathiawar region (Rajkot district) of the princely state of Gujarat in 1824. ",
            "keyString": "684733s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following act was the revision of Vernacular Act?",
            "optionA": "  Indian Press act, 1910 ",
            "optionB": "  Newspaper Act, 1908 ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Press Act of 1910 was legislation promulgated in British India imposing strict censorship on all kinds of publications. The measure was brought into effect to curtail the influence of Indian vernacular and English language in promoting support for what was considered radical Indian nationalism. ",
            "keyString": "684759s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established Prarthana Samaj?",
            "optionA": "  Ishwar Chandra Vidya Sagar ",
            "optionB": "  Derozio ",
            "optionC": "  David Hare ",
            "optionD": "  Athmaram Panduranga with the help of Keshav Chandra Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrarthana Samaj, or \"Prayer Society\" in Sanskrit, was a movement for religious and social reform in Bombay based on earlier reform movements. Prarthana Samaj was founded by Atmaram Pandurang in 1867 when Kesab Chandra sen visited Maharashtra, with an aim to make people believe in one God and worship only one God. ",
            "keyString": "684780s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following initiated reforms among Muslims?",
            "optionA": "  Muhammad Iqbal ",
            "optionB": "  Sayyid Ahmad Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Naoriji Furdonji ",
            "optionD": "  Altaf Husain Hali ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important movement for the spread of modern education and social reform among Muslims was started by Syed Ahmad Khan (1817-1898). The leadership of the League was taken over by Sir Muhammad Iqbal, who in 1930 first put forward the demand for a separate Muslim state in India. The \"Two-Nation Theory\", the belief that Hindus and Muslims were two different nations who could not live in one country, gained popularity among Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "731767s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Narayana Guru attained the age of sixty, his birthday was observed throughout the west-coast from Mangalore to __________",
            "optionA": "  Varkala ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "optionC": "  Kottayam ",
            "optionD": "  Calicut ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Narayana Guru attained the age of sixty, his birth day was observed throughout the west-coast from Mangalore to Sri Lanka. ",
            "keyString": "731806s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________formed the Arya Mahila Samaj in Pune?",
            "optionA": "  Ramabai Saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Swarnakumari Devi ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Chelmsford ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter Medhvi's death (1882), Ramabai moved to Pune where she founded Arya Mahila Samaj (Arya Women's Society). The purpose of the society was to promote the cause of women's education and deliverance from the oppression of child marriage. ",
            "keyString": "731821s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Arya Samaj is against",
            "optionA": "  Existence of God ",
            "optionB": "  Rituals and idol-worship ",
            "optionC": "  Hinduism ",
            "optionD": "  Islam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArya samaj was founded by Swami Dayananda Saraswati, in 1875 they opposed the rituals andidol-worship. Members of the Arya Samaj believe in one God and reject the worship of idols. ",
            "keyString": "731833s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following provisions are included under female infanticide act of 1870?\nI. Declared female infanticide illegal equivalent to murder\nII. Parents to register the birth of all babies compulsorily.\nIII. Verification of female children after some years of birth particularly in areas where the custom is still prevalent",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  All the above statement ",
            "optionC": "  Only II and III ",
            "optionD": "  Only I and II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder female infanticide act of 1870 it declared female infanticide illegal equivalent to murder. It asked parents to register the birth of all babies compulsorily. It asked for verification of female children after some years of birth particularly in areas where the custom is still prevalent. ",
            "keyString": "731845s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement regarding Henry Vivian Derozio are correct?\nI. He is an Anglo-Indian\nII. Was called first nationalist poet of modern India\nIII. He taught at Hindu college and was later removed because of his radicalism",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only I and II ",
            "optionC": "  Only II and III ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHenry Vivian Derozio was an Anglo-Indian. He was called first nationalist poet of modern India. He taught at Hindu college and was later removed because of his radicalism. ",
            "keyString": "774937s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the paths chosen by Ramakrishna Paramahamsa towards salvation",
            "optionA": "  Gyana marg ",
            "optionB": "  Belief in one single god monotheism ",
            "optionC": "  Vedas and Upanishads are the only way to salvation ",
            "optionD": "  Renunciation, meditation and devotion ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRenunciation, meditation and devotion are the paths chosen by Ramakrishna Paramahamsa towards salvation. ",
            "keyString": "774971s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following British Officials suppressed the Revolt of Jhansi?",
            "optionA": "  Colin Campbell ",
            "optionB": "  Henry Havelock ",
            "optionC": "  Henry Lawrence ",
            "optionD": "  Hugh Rose ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBritish Officials Hugh Rose suppressed the Revolt of Jhansi. ",
            "keyString": "774985s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are correct issues related to the Raja Rammohan Roy?\nI. Abolition of Sati\nII. Abolition of Child marriage\nIII. Widow Remarriage",
            "optionA": "  I Only ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionC": "  I and II ",
            "optionD": "  II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Rammohan Roy supported women's rights. He was known for his efforts to abolish Sati Pratha (Hindu funeral practice in which widows were compelled to sacrifice themselves with their husband's pyre) and child marriage. Due to his unending efforts, Sati was declared illegal in 1829. ",
            "keyString": "774997s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the governor-general during the Revolt of 1857?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Canning ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Irwin ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Lytton ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Willington ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Canning served as Governor General of India from 1856 to 1862. During his tenure, the Government of India Act, 1858 was passed which created the office of Viceroy to be held by the same person who was Governor General of India. Thus, Lord Canning also served as first Viceroy of India. ",
            "keyString": "775011s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Social reforms were a major task of the theosophical society. With respect to Indian traditions and culture, which one does not find its occurrence in the societal activities?\nI. Resistance to child marriage.\nII. Resistance to widow remarriage.\nIII. Spread of education.\nIV. Abolition of caste and Untouchability.\nV. Accommodation of conversion in religious faith.",
            "optionA": "  I and III ",
            "optionB": "  II and IV ",
            "optionC": "  II, V ",
            "optionD": "  Only V ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSocial reforms were a major task of the theosophical society. With respect to Indian traditions and culture, the one that does not find its occurrence in the societal activities are Resistance to widow remarriage and Accommodation of conversion in religious faith ",
            "keyString": "822768s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about Prarthana Samaj?",
            "optionA": "  The Prarthana Samaj was founded in Bombay in1867 ",
            "optionB": "  The\u00a0Prarthana Samaj was founded by Athmaram panduranga (with the help of Keshav Chandra Sen) ",
            "optionC": "  The main aim behind the establishment of the Prarthana Samaj was to make people believe in one God and worship only one God ",
            "optionD": "  This society was against the widow remarriage ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis society was not against the widow remarriage. Their comprehensive reform movement has led many impressive projects of cultural change and social reform in Western India, such as the improvement of the lot of women and depressed classes, an end to the caste system, abolition of child marriages and infanticide, educational opportunities for women, and remarriage of widows. ",
            "keyString": "822803s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements regarding Ahmadiya Movement is/are correct?\nI. Founded by Mirza Ghulam Ahmed\nII. It described itself as standard bearer of Mohammedan Renaissance\nIII. Based itself on the principles of Brahmo Samaj\nIV. Opposed jihad and worked for spreading western liberal education among Indian Muslims",
            "optionA": "  Only I and II ",
            "optionB": "  Only I and IV ",
            "optionC": "  Only I, II and IV ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAhmadiya Movement was founded by Mirza Ghulam Ahmed. It described itself as standard bearer of Mohammedan Renaissance. It is based itself on the principles of Brahmo Samaj. It Opposed jihad and worked for spreading western liberal education among Indian Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "822818s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gurudevan participated in the anniversary of the Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam held at Palluruthy in__________",
            "optionA": "  1913 ",
            "optionB": "  1917 ",
            "optionC": "  1927 ",
            "optionD": "  1948 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGurudevan participated in the anniversary of the Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam held at Palluruthy in 1927. It was a splendid meeting which demonstrated the sincere, devout faith of the people in Gurudevan. T. K. Madhavan was one of the chief architects of this meeting. ",
            "keyString": "822834s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The following are the lessons taught to masses i.e. Muslim women in particular",
            "optionA": "  Urged the Muslims to give up medieval customs and ways of thought and behavior ",
            "optionB": "  Removal of purdah and spread of education ",
            "optionC": "  Both A and B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuslim women in particular urged the Muslims to give up medieval customs and ways of thought and behavior and removal of purdah and spread of education. ",
            "keyString": "822845s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements related to the cause of 1857 revolt.\nI. It was a great disparity in salaries between the Indian and European soldiers.\nII. The Indian sepoys were treated with contempt by their European officers.\nIII. The sepoys were sent to distant parts of the empire, but were not paid any extra allowance.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  I, II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cause of 1857 revolt were - It was a great disparity in salaries between the Indian and European soldiers. The Indian sepoys were treated with contempt by their European officers. The sepoys were sent to distant parts of the empire, but were not paid any extra allowance. ",
            "keyString": "882154s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following ideas propagated through Ramakrishna Mission?\nI. Social and religious reform\nII. Women education\nIII. Doctrine of service\nIV. Service of jiva and worship of Shiva",
            "optionA": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionB": "  II, III and IV ",
            "optionC": "  III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  I, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ideas propagated through Ramakrishna Mission were Social and religious reform, Doctrine of service, Service of jiva and worship of Shiva. ",
            "keyString": "882800s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statement (s) related to the administrative causes of 1857 revolt.\nI. Deprivation of the traditional ruling classes of their luxury due to the establishment of the company's suzerainty over the Indian states.\nII. Introduction of new and revenue system which snatched the land from cultivator and gave it to the moneylender or traitor.\nIII. Lord Canning's announcement to that Mughals would lose the title of King and be mere Princess.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Both I and III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe administrative causes of 1857 revolt were Deprivation of the traditional ruling classes of their luxury due to the establishment of the company's suzerainty over the Indian states, Introduction of new and revenue system which snatched the land from cultivator and gave it to the moneylender or traitor. ",
            "keyString": "883390s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following cannot be said to be a cardinal principle of the theosophical society?",
            "optionA": "  It questioned the ancient philosophies that dominated the Indian thinking ",
            "optionB": "  Aimed Hindu spiritual wisdom through western enlightenment ",
            "optionC": "  It believed in the existence of unique connections between god and every being ",
            "optionD": "  It believed in the possibility of reincarnation and karma ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt does not questioned the ancient philosophies that dominated the Indian thinking. ",
            "keyString": "883897s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is called \"Magna Carta of English Education in India\"?",
            "optionA": "  Wood's Dispatch ",
            "optionB": "  Macaulay Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Vernacular Act ",
            "optionD": "  Both A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Wood's Despatch is known as the Magna Carta of Indian Education. It was the Act of 1854, which was passed by the British.The despatch was presented by the Secretary of State, Sir Charles Wood, to the directors of the East India Company (as there was Company's rule at that time). ",
            "keyString": "884383s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is one of the social reasons for 1857 revolt?",
            "optionA": "  The English could not establish any social relationship with the Indians ",
            "optionB": "  The racial arrogance of the British created a difference between the rulers and the ruled ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  The company's trade policy destroyed Indian handicrafts ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe social reasons for 1857 revolt was that the english could not establish any social relationship with the Indians and the racial arrogance of the british created a difference between the rulers and the ruled. ",
            "keyString": "959315s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following leaders is not associated with the Brahmo Samaj?",
            "optionA": "  Debendranath Tagore ",
            "optionB": "  Keshab Chandra Sen ",
            "optionC": "  Raja ram Mohan Rai ",
            "optionD": "  Atma Ram Pandurang ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAtmaram Pandurang or Atmaram Pandurang Turkhadekar was an Indian physician and social reformer who founded the Prarthana Samaj and was one of the two Indian co-founders of the Bombay Natural History Society. ",
            "keyString": "959619s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Henry Vivian Derozio started young Bengal movement with the inspiration of which revolutionary ideas?",
            "optionA": "  Industrial revolution ",
            "optionB": "  French revolution ",
            "optionC": "  American Revolution ",
            "optionD": "  Marxian theory ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHenry Vivian Derozio started young Bengal movement with the inspiration of French revolution. ",
            "keyString": "960288s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following were the ideas popularized through theosophical society\nI. Doctrine of trans-migration of souls\nII. Universal brotherhood of man\nIII. Reincarnation and Karma, and drew inspiration from philosophy of Upanishads and samkhya, yoga and Vedanta school\nIV. Against foreign rule",
            "optionA": "  Only III ",
            "optionB": "  Only I and III ",
            "optionC": "  Only I, II and III ",
            "optionD": "  All the four are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ideas popularized through theosophical society were Doctrine of trans-migration of souls, Universal brotherhood of man and Reincarnation and Karma, and drew inspiration from philosophy of Upanishads and samkhya, yoga and Vedanta school. ",
            "keyString": "960564s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The theosophical society was marked by the close understanding of the cosmos and the mundane life. Which among the listed options is not a part of their curriculum?",
            "optionA": "  Divinity ",
            "optionB": "  Salvation ",
            "optionC": "  Means of enlightenment ",
            "optionD": "  Mystic superstition ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMystic superstition is not the part of the theosophical society that was marked by the close understanding of the cosmos and the mundane life. ",
            "keyString": "960760s48m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Dayanand Saraswati established the Arya Samaj in 1875 at",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Lahore ",
            "optionC": "  Nagpur ",
            "optionD": "  Ahmadnagar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Dayanand established the Arya Samaj on April 7, 1875 in Bombay, with 10 principles that are beautifully based purely on God, soul and nature. The organisation brought about immense changes in the religious perceptions of Indians. ",
            "keyString": "55581s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following reformer was associated with Prarthana Samaj?",
            "optionA": "  M. G. Ranade ",
            "optionB": "  Bhandarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Atmaram Pandurang ",
            "optionD": "  Chandavarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAtmaram Pandurang or Atmaram Pandurang Turkhadekar (or just Turkhad in English publications) (1823-1898) was an Indian physician and social reformer who founded the Prarthana Samaj and was one of the two Indian co-founders (the other being Sakharam Arjun) of the Bombay Natural History Society. ",
            "keyString": "55614s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following statements is/ are not correct?\nI. The theosophical society preached the Aryan philosophy and religion\nII. It laid great emphasis on the Vedas and Upanishad.\nIII. It considered Hinduism to be the best religion and the only means to attain salvation.\nIV. It called for universal brotherhood.\nV. The Upanishads revealed the essence of life",
            "optionA": "  I, III and V ",
            "optionB": "  II, II and V ",
            "optionC": "  Only III ",
            "optionD": "  I and III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe theosophical society does not considered Hinduism to be the best religion and the only means to attain salvation. ",
            "keyString": "55629s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy was the founder of the__________",
            "optionA": "  Brahmo Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Arya Samaj ",
            "optionC": "  Ramakrishna Mission ",
            "optionD": "  Theosophical society ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRam Mohan Roy. Raja Ram Mohan Roy (22 May 1772 \u2013 27 September 1833) was one of the founders of the Brahmo Sabha, the precursor of the Brahmo Samaj, a socio-religious reform movement in the Indian subcontinent. ",
            "keyString": "55646s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The original name of Swami Dayananda Saraswati was",
            "optionA": "  Abhi Shankar ",
            "optionB": "  Gowri Shankar ",
            "optionC": "  Daya Shankar ",
            "optionD": "  Mula Shankar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHis original name was Mul Shankar because he was born in Dhanu Rashi and Mul Nakshatra. His father was Karshanji Lalji Kapadi, and his mother was Amrutbai. ",
            "keyString": "55657s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the reasons for which Wahabi / Walliullah movement was started?",
            "optionA": "  Spreading education among Muslim women ",
            "optionB": "  Encouraging to give up puradh system ",
            "optionC": "  Reviving Muslim principles in response to western influences ",
            "optionD": "  Propagating Quran as the only source ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was also known as \u2018Walliullah Movement\u2019 which started in response to the western influences and was inspired by the teachings of Shah Walliullah who was regarded as the first Indian Muslim leader. The entire movement was moving around the legacy of Islam- 'Quran and Hadis'. ",
            "keyString": "140447s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the original name of Dayananda Saraswati?",
            "optionA": "  Malku das ",
            "optionB": "  Mul Shankara ",
            "optionC": "  Narendra ",
            "optionD": "  Dadu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHis original name was Mul Shankar because he was born in Dhanu Rashi and Mul Nakshatra. His father was Karshanji Lalji Kapadi, and his mother was Amrutbai. ",
            "keyString": "140585s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are the main aim/s of Young Bengal Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Inspire pupil to think freely and rationally ",
            "optionB": "  Question all authority and oppose decadent customs and traditions ",
            "optionC": "  Love liberty, equality and freedom ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey wanted to promote radical ideas through teachings and by organizing debates and discussions on Literature, History, Philosophy and Science. The basic motto of Derozio was to spread intellectual revolution among young students. He was a great propounder of liberal thinking. ",
            "keyString": "140639s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Temple entry movement started mainly in Kerala aimed at which of the following",
            "optionA": "  Allowing untouchables to Hindu temples and roads ",
            "optionB": "  Keeping the monopoly of temples to Brahmin class ",
            "optionC": "  Allowing women to enter temple ",
            "optionD": "  Sanskrit lessons to be imparted only to Brahmin family members and others to be devoid of it in order to preserve its purity ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Temple Entry Proclamation was issued by Maharaja Chithira Thirunal Balarama Varma in 1936 and abolished the ban on the so called 'low caste people' or avarnas from entering Hindu temples in the Princely State of Travancore, now part of Kerala, India. ",
            "keyString": "140727s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sir Huge Rose described whom as 'the best and bravest military leader of the rebel'?",
            "optionA": "  Begum Hazrat Mahal ",
            "optionB": "  Rani Laxmi Bai ",
            "optionC": "  Kunwar Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Bahadur Shah Zafar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Huge Rose described Rani Laxmi Bai as 'the best and bravest military leader of the rebel'. ",
            "keyString": "140781s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following reform is the legislative contribution of Raja Rammohan Roy?",
            "optionA": "  Abolition of sati ",
            "optionB": "  Indianisation of superior services ",
            "optionC": "  Reduction of export duties on Indian goods ",
            "optionD": "  Abolition of east India company's trading rights ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Rammohan Roy supported women's rights. He was known for his efforts to abolish Sati Pratha (Hindu funeral practice in which widows were compelled to sacrifice themselves with their husband's pyre) and child marriage. Due to his unending efforts, Sati was declared illegal in 1829. ",
            "keyString": "216610s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about Raja Ram Mohan Roy?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy was born in a well-to-do family in Bengal, probably in 1772 ",
            "optionB": "  He died in Indian in 1833 ",
            "optionC": "  He was given the title of Raja by the Mughal Emperor ",
            "optionD": "  He started the newspaper named \"Sambad Kaumudi\" ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRam Mohan Roy was originally buried on 18 October 1833, in the grounds of Stapleton Grove where he had died of meningitis on 27 September 1833.",
            "keyString": "216649s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Theosophical movement though not very successful helped in contributing to developments in society. Which of the following are those developments?\nI. Women upliftment and recognized their importance\nII. Provided self respect needed to fight British colonial rule\nIII. Did not provide any contribution as they realized that they were giving false sense of pride",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Only III ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTheosophical movement though not very successful helped in contributing to developments in society it provided self respect needed to fight British colonial rule. ",
            "keyString": "216668s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who advocated the concept of one caste, one religion and one God for all?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Narayan Guru ",
            "optionC": "  Periyar ",
            "optionD": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Narayana Guru preached the doctrine of 'One caste, One religion, One God.' Its worth note that one of his athiest disciples, Sahadaran Ayyapan, changed into 'no religion, no caste and no God for mankind. ",
            "keyString": "216734s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What did Raja Ram Mohan Roy actively seek reforms in?",
            "optionA": "  Promoting intercaste marriages ",
            "optionB": "  Teaching the Vedas in schools ",
            "optionC": "  Ending the practice of Sati ",
            "optionD": "  Building more temples ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Rammohan Roy supported women's rights. He was known for his efforts to abolish Sati Pratha (Hindu funeral practice in which widows were compelled to sacrifice themselves with their husband's pyre) and child marriage. Due to his unending efforts, Sati was declared illegal in 1829. ",
            "keyString": "216759s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the innovative means used by Ishwar Chandra Vidya Sagar to bring Sanskrit education to all?",
            "optionA": "  Devised new Bengali primer ",
            "optionB": "  Brought new prose style ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  Continued the same method without any new innovation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe innovative means used by Ishwar Chandra Vidya Sagar to bring Sanskrit education to all were Devised new Bengali primer and it brought new prose style. ",
            "keyString": "286666s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The sepoy mutiny of 1857 occurred during the Governor Generalship to",
            "optionA": "  Break priestly monopoly of scriptural knowledge(Sanskrit) and opening to non- Brahmins ",
            "optionB": "  Charles wood dispatch on education, influenced it towards female education ",
            "optionC": "  Lady Hardinge medical college at Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sepoy mutiny of 1857 occurred during the Governor Generalship to break priestly monopoly of scriptural knowledge(Sanskrit) and opening to non- Brahmins and Charles wood dispatch on education, influenced it towards female education. ",
            "keyString": "286700s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about Arya Samaj?",
            "optionA": "  The Arya Samajists opposed child marriages and encouraged remarriage of widows ",
            "optionB": "  It was founded in 1875 ",
            "optionC": "  Its main motive was to promote faith in one God ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above is correct ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArya Samaj is an Indian Hindu reform movement that promotes values and practices based on the belief in the infallible authority of the Vedas. The samaj was founded by the sannyasi Dayanand Saraswati on 10 April 1875. Members of the Arya Samaj believe in one God and reject the worship of idols. ",
            "keyString": "286716s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the main reasons for failure of Young Bengal Movement?\nI. Suppression by British new law\nII. Did not involve peasant cause\nIII. Radicalism was bookish in character and did not develop links with masses",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both II and III ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main reasons for failure of Young Bengal Movement were that it did not involve peasant cause and Radicalism was bookish in character and did not develop links with masses. ",
            "keyString": "286728s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the prominent leader in Lucknow during the Revolt of 1857?",
            "optionA": "  Begum Hazrat Mahal ",
            "optionB": "  Rani Laxmi Bai ",
            "optionC": "  Kuar Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Bahadur Shah Zafar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Mutiny of 1857. During the Indian Mutiny, from 1857 to 1858, Begum Hazrat Mahal's band of supporters, led by Raja Jailal Singh, rebelled against the forces of the British; later, they seized control of Lucknow and she declared her son, Birjis Qadra, as the ruler (Wali) of Oudh. ",
            "keyString": "286742s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aravippuram movement which is considered as a precursor to all south Indian socio religious reform movement started in which of the following places?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Andra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAravippuram movement which is considered as a precursor to all south Indian socio religious reform movement started in Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "359879s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Charles wood's despatch deals with which of the following issues?",
            "optionA": "  Child marriages ",
            "optionB": "  Female education ",
            "optionC": "  Abolition of sati ",
            "optionD": "  Female infanticide ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Charles Wood, the President of the Board of Control, had an important effect on spreading English learning and female education in India. ",
            "keyString": "360015s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Brahmo Samaj split?",
            "optionA": "  1866 ",
            "optionB": "  1826 ",
            "optionC": "  1843 ",
            "optionD": "  1857 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1866, Keshub Chandra Sen organised the more radical \"Brahmo Samaj of India\" with overtones of Christianity. ",
            "keyString": "360064s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was Narayana Guru born?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarayana Guru (ca. 1854 \u2013 20 September 1928), was a social reformer of India. He was born into a family of the Ezhava caste in an era when people from such communities, which were regarded as Avarna, faced much injustice in the caste-ridden society of Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "360105s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is said that Ishwar Chandra Vidya Sagar's contribution to making of modern India is many sided. Which of the following aspects contribute to it?",
            "optionA": "  Farmers and depressed class upliftment ",
            "optionB": "  New methodology of teaching Sanskrit ",
            "optionC": "  Uplifting downtrodden women, abolishing child marriage , widow re marriage ",
            "optionD": "  Both B and C ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is said that Ishwar Chandra Vidya Sagar's contribution to making of modern India is many sidedand it was new methodology of teaching Sanskrit. Uplifting downtrodden women, abolishing child marriage , widow re-marriage. ",
            "keyString": "360142s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Vivekananda's contribution to society and educating masses is through following ways:\nI. Condemned caste system and current rituals and superstitions\nII. Criticized for having lost touch with rest of world and for becoming stagnant and mummified\nIII. Subscribed to Vedanta which he considered fully rational system",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Only III ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda's contribution to society and educating masses is through following ways: He condemned caste system and current rituals and superstitions. He criticized for having lost touch with rest of world and for becoming stagnant and mummified. He subscribed to Vedanta which he considered fully rational system. ",
            "keyString": "432198s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raja Rammohan Roy's contribution to education are:\nI. Assisted David Hare in setting Hindu college\nII. English school at Calcutta was maintained at his own cost\nIII. Established Vedanta College which taught only western social and physical sciences",
            "optionA": "  Only III ",
            "optionB": "  Both II and III ",
            "optionC": "  Only I and II ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Rammohan Roy's contribution to education are that he assisted David Hare in setting Hindu college and English school at Calcutta was maintained at his own cost. ",
            "keyString": "432237s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aligarh Movement towards the end revented its followers from joining the national movement. Which of the following reasons made it to take this decision though it initially propagated for unity?",
            "optionA": "  It felt that immediate political progress was not possible and British Government couldn't be easily dislodged ",
            "optionB": "  Indians are educationally forward so in order to suppress them their activities need to discouraged ",
            "optionC": "  Gain support of British officials ",
            "optionD": "  National movement is waste of time so should concentrate on other works ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt felt that immediate political progress was not possible and British Government couldn't be easily dislodged. ",
            "keyString": "432257s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the greatest contribution of Ishwar Chand Vidyasagar in the social reforms in India?",
            "optionA": "  He ensured the widow's marriage and girl's education ",
            "optionB": "  Help in the abolition of Sati Pratha ",
            "optionC": "  Established the Brahma Samaj ",
            "optionD": "  He adopted 100 villages to relocate them from Andhra Pradesh to Bengal for better life ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe greatest contribution of Ishwar Chand Vidyasagar in the social reforms in India was that he ensured the widow's marriage and girl's education. ",
            "keyString": "432273s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In __________, a man named Raja Ram Mohan Roy founded an organization called 'Brahma Samaj'",
            "optionA": "  1628 ",
            "optionB": "  1728 ",
            "optionC": "  1828 ",
            "optionD": "  1928 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Ram Mohan Roy was the founder of the Brahmo Samaj at Kolkata in 1828. His efforts actually led to the resumption of the ethical principles of the Vedanta school of philosophy. He co-founded the Calcutta Unitarian Society. The title 'Raja' was bestowed upon him by the Mughal Emperor, Akbar II. ",
            "keyString": "432288s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following principle propagated by Aligarh school which helped in bringing reforms in Muslims?\nI. Intolerance to other religions and religious texts\nII. Quran was the only authoritative work for Islam and all others are secondary. Therefore said belief in only Islam\nIII. Incorporate modern western thought",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionC": "  Both II and III ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe principle propagated by Aligarh school which helped in bringing reforms in Muslims are Quran was the only authoritative work for Islam and all others are secondary. Therefore said belief in only Islam and incorporate modern western thought. ",
            "keyString": "524187s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader associated with Barout in Uttar Pradesh during 1857 revolts?",
            "optionA": "  Shah Mal ",
            "optionB": "  Maulavi Ahamadullah Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Tatya Tope ",
            "optionD": "  Veer Kuwar Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe leader associated with Barout in Uttar Pradesh during 1857 revolts was Shah Mal. ",
            "keyString": "524222s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following works taken up even after the decline of the movement?",
            "optionA": "  Fight for women's rights and education ",
            "optionB": "  Carry forward Raja Ram Mohan Roy's tradition of public education on social, economic and political questions ",
            "optionC": "  Took up farmers issues and fought for their better treatment and against oppressive zamindars ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe works taken up even after the decline of the movement were Fight for women's rights and education, Carry forward Raja Ram Mohan Roy's tradition of public education on social, economic and political questions, Took up farmers issues and fought for their better treatment and against oppressive zamindars. ",
            "keyString": "524239s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Prarthana Samaj had been established by",
            "optionA": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  Keshub Chandra Sen ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionD": "  MN Roy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrarthana Samaj, or \"Prayer Society\" in Sanskrit, was a movement for religious and social reform in Bombay based on earlier reform movements. Prarthana Samaj was founded by Atmaram Pandurang in 1867 when Kesab Chandra sen visited Maharashtra, with an aim to make people believe in one God and worship only one God. ",
            "keyString": "524253s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the contribution of Sayyid Ahmad Khan towards education of Muslims?\nI. Brought translation of books to Urdu\nII. Founded Aligarh Muhammedan Anglo-Oriental College for spreading western sciences\nIII. Encouraged people to send their children to schools",
            "optionA": "  Only II ",
            "optionB": "  Only I and II ",
            "optionC": "  Only I and III ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe contribution of Sayyid Ahmad Khan towards education of Muslims were that it brought translation of books to Urdu, it founded Aligarh Muhammedan Anglo-Oriental College for spreading western sciences, it encouraged people to send their children to schools. ",
            "keyString": "524266s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raja Rammohan Roy and Brahma Samaj which of the following statements regarding Raja Rammohan Roy are correct?\nI. Considered as father of Indian renaissance\nII. Started Brahmo Samaj\nIII. Set up Atmiya Sabha in Calcutta\nIV. Translated Vedas and five Upanishads to Bengali language",
            "optionA": "  Only II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I, II, III ",
            "optionC": "  I, II and IV ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Rammohan Roy is considered as father of Indian renaissance. He started Brahmo Samaj. He set up Atmiya Sabha in Calcutta. He translated Vedas and five Upanishads to Bengali language. ",
            "keyString": "570727s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sri Narayana Guru Swamy initiated a programme of action called Sri Narayana Guru Dharma Paripalana yogam which took up issues regarding depressed classes, contains which of the issues?\nI. Encouraging inter caste marriages\nII. Right of admission to public schools\nIII. Recruitment to government schools\nIV. Access to temples and roads",
            "optionA": "  Only II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionC": "  I, II and IV ",
            "optionD": "  All four are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Narayana Guru Swamy initiated a programme of action called Sri Narayana Guru Dharma Paripalana yogam which took up issues regarding depressed classes, contains encouraging inter caste marriages. Right of admission to public schools. Recruitment to government schools. Access to temples and roads. ",
            "keyString": "570772s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the author of the book \"The First Indian War of Independence- 1857-59\"?",
            "optionA": "  Karl Marx ",
            "optionB": "  Syed Ahmad Khan ",
            "optionC": "  R. Mazumdar ",
            "optionD": "  S. N. Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKarl Marx is the author of the book \"The First Indian War of Independence- 1857-59\". ",
            "keyString": "570792s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Concerning the caste system, __________said the following to Narayana Guru: \"The casteHindus and the low caste-Hindus are both the sons of Hinduism. The caste-Hindu is the elder brother who shoulders responsibility, and he therefore exercises certain privileges. The low casteHindu is his younger brother who is to be cared for. If the elder brother turns out to be somewhat rough and aggressive that should not make the younger brother a runaway from his mother Hinduism.\"",
            "optionA": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  Tilak ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi said the following to Narayana Guru: \"The caste Hindus and the low caste-Hindus are both the sons of Hinduism. The caste-Hindu is the elder brother who shoulders responsibility, and he therefore exercises certain privileges. The low caste Hindu is his younger brother who is to be cared for. If the elder brother turns out to be somewhat rough and aggressive that should not make the younger brother a runaway from his mother Hinduism.\" ",
            "keyString": "570808s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Paramahamsa Mandali primarily aimed at breaking caste rules was founded in which of the following places",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was the first socio-religious organization of Maharashtra. Founded in 1849 Maharashtra, the founders of these mandli believed in one god. They were primarily interested in breaking caste rules. At their meetings food cooked by lower caste people was taken by the members. ",
            "keyString": "570824s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy was born on May 22, 1772 in village Radhanagar in the District of Hooghly in __________",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  MP ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Rammohan Roy was born on May 22, 1772, in a Brahmin family in the village of Radhanagar near Krishnanagar in Hooghly district (Bengal Presidency). ",
            "keyString": "674630s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy was given the title 'Raja' by the__________",
            "optionA": "  Mughals ",
            "optionB": "  British ",
            "optionC": "  French ",
            "optionD": "  Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1828, he launched Brahmo Sabha with Devendranath Tagore. By 1828, he had become a well known figure in India. In 1830, he had gone to England as an envoy of the Mughal Emperor, Akbar Shah II, who invested him with the title of Raja to the court of King William IV. ",
            "keyString": "674662s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements regarding Gyana Prasarak Mandalis or student literary and scientific societies is / are correct?\nI. Formed by common people to educate youth\nII. Had two branches Marathi and Guajarati\nIII. Aimed to start schools for girls.\nIV. Organized lectures to propagate their ideas",
            "optionA": "  I and II only ",
            "optionB": "  I III and IV only ",
            "optionC": "  II and III only ",
            "optionD": "  II, III\u00a0and\u00a0IV ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statements regarding Gyana Prasarak Mandalis or student literary and scientific societies that are correct are it had two branches Marathi and Guajarati, it aimed to start schools for girls and it organized lectures to propagate their ideas. ",
            "keyString": "674677s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main cause for the Instant popularity of the Arya Samaj was that",
            "optionA": "  It represented the purified form of Hinduism ",
            "optionB": "  It supported and worded for the cause of western education ",
            "optionC": "  It combined the opposition to the evil practices of Hinduism with an aggressive assertion of the superiority of the Vedic religion and Indian thought over all other faiths ",
            "optionD": "  It gave a call to its followers to go back to the Vedas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main cause for the Instant popularity of the Arya Samaj was that it combined the opposition to the evil practices of Hinduism with an aggressive assertion of the superiority of the Vedic religion and Indian thought over all other faiths. ",
            "keyString": "674694s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following reasons can be attributed to the success of Ramakrishna mission?",
            "optionA": "  Focused mainly on teachings of Upanishads and Vedas ",
            "optionB": "  Popularized the saying\" for our own motherland a junction of both Hinduism and Islam is necessary\" ",
            "optionC": "  Though a religious body never considered itself as a sect of Hinduism ",
            "optionD": "  Worked for upliftment of depressed classes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe reasons that can be attributed to the success of Ramakrishna mission was though a religious body never considered itself as a sect of Hinduism. ",
            "keyString": "674706s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the author of the book \"Satyarth Prakash\"?",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Rajaram Mohan Ray ",
            "optionC": "  Mahadev Govind Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  Ramakrishna Bhandarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyarth Prakash (\"The Light of Meaning of the Truth\" or The Light of Truth) is a 1875 book written originally in Hindi by Maharishi Dayanand Saraswati, a renowned religious and social reformer and the founder of Arya Samaj. It is considered one of his major scholarly works. ",
            "keyString": "724322s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Satyashodhak Samaj was founded by whom?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jyotibha Phule ",
            "optionC": "  Dr. ",
            "optionD": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJyotibha Phule was the founder of Satyashodhak Samar in Pune 1873, the Purpose of this samaj was to liberate the Shudra Untouchable castes from exploitation and oppression. ",
            "keyString": "724431s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the role of Tatia Tope in 1857 mutiny?\nI. He was commander-in-chief of the army of Nana Saheb\nII. He organized Bhils of Panchamahal region against the British\nIII. He helped Begum Hazrat Mahal to capture Awadh",
            "optionA": "  II only ",
            "optionB": "  I and II only ",
            "optionC": "  II and III only ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe role of Tatia Tope in 1857 mutiny was commander-in-chief of the army of Nana Saheb and he has to organize Bhils of Panchamahal region against the British. ",
            "keyString": "724454s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first lawful Hindu widow remarriage among upper castes in our country was celebrated under which of the following reformer",
            "optionA": "  Raja Rammohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  Keshub Chandra Sen ",
            "optionC": "  Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar ",
            "optionD": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first lawful Hindu widow remarriage among the upper castes in India was celebrated in Calcutta on 7 December 1856 under the inspiration and supervision of Vidyasagar. In 1850, Vidyasagar protested against child-marriage. All his life, he campaigned against polygamy. ",
            "keyString": "724477s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Faraizi Movement which aimed at removing social reforms in muslims started in which of the following regions?",
            "optionA": "  East Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShariatullah founded the Faraizi movement which was a religious reform movement in the 19th century for Bengali Muslims. The term Faraizi was taken from fard which means standing for compulsory and mandatory duties ordained by Allah. It started in East Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "724497s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  Rajaram Mohan Rai set up Brahmo Sabha in 1828 ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmo Sabha forbade idol-worship and discarded meaningless rites and rituals ",
            "optionC": "  Rajaram Mohan Rai worked to abolish child marriage ",
            "optionD": "  Sati Pratha was abolished in 1829 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Ram Mohun Roy was the first one to raise his voice against the evil systems of sati, polygamy, child marriage, widow remarriage and oppression of women. ",
            "keyString": "839781s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following names is not associated with the theosophical society?",
            "optionA": "  Col. Occolt ",
            "optionB": "  Madame Blavatsky ",
            "optionC": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionD": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak, born as Keshav Gangadhar Tilak, was an Indian nationalist, teacher, lawyer and an independence activist. He was the first leader of the Indian Independence Movement. The British colonial authorities called him \"The father of the Indian unrest.\" ",
            "keyString": "840074s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Year of the Battle of Plassey is __________",
            "optionA": "  1557 ",
            "optionB": "  1657 ",
            "optionC": "  1757 ",
            "optionD": "  1857 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Plassey was a major battle that took place on 23 June 1757 at Palashi, Bengal. It was an important British East India Company victory over the Nawab of Bengal and his French allies. ",
            "keyString": "840309s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Year of the Battle of Buxar is__________",
            "optionA": "  1764 ",
            "optionB": "  1767 ",
            "optionC": "  1784 ",
            "optionD": "  1864 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Buxar was fought on 22 October 1764 between the forces under the command of the British East India Company, led by Hector Munro, and the combined armies of Mir Qasim, Nawab of Bengal till 1763; the Nawab of Awadh; and the Mughal Emperor Shah Alam II. ",
            "keyString": "840544s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hyder Ali was the ruler of __________",
            "optionA": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionB": "  Mysore ",
            "optionC": "  Cochi ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHyder Ali , Haidarali (c. 1720 \u2013 7 December 1782) was the Sultan and de facto ruler of the Kingdom of Mysore in southern India. ",
            "keyString": "840787s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main purpose of Brahmo Samaj for which it was set up are",
            "optionA": "  Purify Hinduism and to preach monotheism ",
            "optionB": "  Criticize social evils, oppose idolatry and emphasize human dignity ",
            "optionC": "  Both A and B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Brahmo Samaj was the first important organization of religious reforms. It forbade idol-worship and discarded meaningless rites and rituals. The Samaj also forbade its members from attacking any religion. It purify Hinduism and to preach monotheism. It criticize social evils, oppose idolatry and emphasize human dignity. ",
            "keyString": "950337s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Maharishi Dayanand Saraswati was an important Hindu religious scholar, reformer, and founder of the __________",
            "optionA": "  Arya Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Brahma Samaj ",
            "optionC": "  Ramakrishna Mission ",
            "optionD": "  Theosophical society ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDayananda Sarasvati, original name Mula Sankara, (born 1824, Tankara, Gujarat, India\u2014died October 30, 1883, Ajmer, Rajputana), Hindu ascetic and social reformer who was the founder (1875) of the Arya Samaj (Society of Aryans [Nobles]), a Hindu reform movement advocating a return to the temporal and spiritual authority. ",
            "keyString": "950884s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Raja Ram Mohan Roy established the \"Calcutta Unitarian Committee\".\nII. Social Service League was established by Mahadev Govind Ranade.\nIII. Deccan Education Society was founded by Gopal Krishna Gokhale.\nIV. Annie Besant started the Central Hindu School.\nWhich of the above statement(s) is/are correct with reference to the reformers & leaders of India's Struggle for Independence?",
            "optionA": "  I, II & IV ",
            "optionB": "  I & IV ",
            "optionC": "  II & III ",
            "optionD": "  III Only ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Ram Mohan Roy established the \"Calcutta Unitarian Committee\". Annie Besant started the Central Hindu School. ",
            "keyString": "951115s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the Devadasi System prevailed in India?",
            "optionA": "  Southern India ",
            "optionB": "  Northern India ",
            "optionC": "  East India ",
            "optionD": "  West\u00a0India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDevadasi system is a religious practice in south India mostly in Karnataka and Telangana, and partly in Andhra Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "951339s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Swami Dayananda had translated the __________ into Hindi.",
            "optionA": "  Rig Veda and Yajur Veda ",
            "optionB": "  Four Vedas ",
            "optionC": "  Sama Veda and Atharva Veda ",
            "optionD": "  Sama Veda and Yajur Veda ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Dayananda had translated the Rig Veda and Yajur Veda into Hindi. ",
            "keyString": "951532s49m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Bengal Regulation Act of 1829 dealt with which of the following issues primarily",
            "optionA": "  Abolition of sati ",
            "optionB": "  Female infanticide ",
            "optionC": "  Child marriages ",
            "optionD": "  Dowry prohibition ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bengal Sati Regulation which banned the Sati practice in all jurisdictions of British India was passed on December 4, 1829 by the then Governor-General Lord William Bentinck. The regulation described the practice of Sati as revolting to the feelings of human nature. ",
            "keyString": "7294s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is the head of theosophical society in India",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Madan Mohan Malaviya ",
            "optionC": "  Blavatsky ",
            "optionD": "  Did not come to india ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant (1847\u20131933), second President of The Theosophical Society from 1907 to 1933, was described as a \u2018Diamond Soul\u2019, for she had many brilliant facets to her character.She was an outstanding orator of her time, a champion of human freedom, educationist, philanthropist, and author with more than three hundred books and pamphlets to her credit. ",
            "keyString": "7505s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Justice movement was started by?\nI. C. N. Mudaliar\nII. T. M. Nair\nIII. P. Tyagaraja",
            "optionA": "  Only a ",
            "optionB": "  Only b ",
            "optionC": "  By both A and B ",
            "optionD": "  All the three ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Justice Party, officially the South Indian Liberal Federation, was a political party in the Madras Presidency of British India. It was established in on November 20, 1916 in Victoria Memorial Hall in Madras by T. M. Nair and P. Theagaraya Chetty as a result of a series of non-Brahmin conferences and meetings in the presidency. ",
            "keyString": "7683s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1883 Dayananda was invited by the Maharaja of __________ to stay at his palace",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Jodhpur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1883, the Maharaja of Jodhpur Swami, Jaswant Singh II, invited Dayananda to stay at his palace. ",
            "keyString": "7859s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following legislative measures taken till 1861 regarding women rights and marriage are true?\nI. Permitted inter-caste marriage\nII. Daughter to be treated equal with son regarding inheritance\nIII. Equal remuneration to both men and women\nIV. Immoral traffic of women to be illegal",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  II and III ",
            "optionC": "  III, II and I ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe legislative measures taken till 1861 regarding women rights and marriage were that they permitted inter-caste marriage and Daughter to be treated equal with son regarding inheritance. ",
            "keyString": "8031s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is considered as the main reason for division of Brahmo Samaj?",
            "optionA": "  Resolutely opposing Christian missionaries and their work against Hinduism ",
            "optionB": "  Internal conflicts among Debendranath Tagore and Keshub Chandra Sen for including teachings of all religions ",
            "optionC": "  Lack of strong propagator of views ",
            "optionD": "  Opposition by people for disturbing traditional caste practices like abolition of sati, widow remarriage and women education ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main reason for division of Brahmo Samaj was Internal conflicts among Debendranath Tagore and Keshub Chandra Sen for including teachings of all religions. ",
            "keyString": "59037s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is the great disciple of Ramakrishna Paramahamsa and helped in spreading the message that there are many roads to god and salvation and service of god for man was embodiment of god?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Rammohan Roy ",
            "optionB": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Dayananda Saraswati ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwami Vivekananda is the great disciple of Ramakrishna Paramahamsa and helped in spreading the message that there are many roads to god and salvation and service of god for man was embodiment of god. ",
            "keyString": "59292s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of Satyashodhak Samaj?",
            "optionA": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "optionB": "  Gopal Hari Deshmukh ",
            "optionC": "  Mahadew Govind Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  Ramakrishna Bhandarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 24 September 1873, Phule formed Satyashodhak Samaj to focus on rights of depressed groups such as women, the Shudra, and the Dalit. ",
            "keyString": "59512s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The actual name of Dayanand Saraawati, the founder of the Arya Samaj was",
            "optionA": "  Daya Shankar ",
            "optionB": "  Mula Shankar ",
            "optionC": "  Virjanand ",
            "optionD": "  Mool Chandra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe actual name of Dayanand Saraawati, the founder of the Arya Samaj was Mula Shankar. ",
            "keyString": "59716s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Wahabi movement aimed to organize Muslims around two fold ideas, which of the following forms the ideas among them?\nI. Harmony among 4 schools of Muslim which were divided at that time\nII. Recognition of the role of individual conscience in religion as conflicting interpretations were derived from quran and other practices",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above stated ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWahabi movement aimed to organize Muslims around two fold ideas which were Harmony among 4 schools of Muslim which were divided at that time and recognition of the role of individual conscience in religion as conflicting interpretations were derived from quran and other practices. ",
            "keyString": "59914s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Servants of Indian Society started by Gopal Krishna Gokhale was set up with which of the following objectives?",
            "optionA": "  Prepare masses for selfless cause of country and devote their lives if needed ",
            "optionB": "  Train national missionaries for the service of country ",
            "optionC": "  Both the above statement ",
            "optionD": "  Reorganization of Indian society on rational principles ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Servants of Indian Society started by Gopal Krishna Gokhale was set up with which of the objectives to prepare masses for selfless cause of country and devote their lives if needed and to train national missionaries for the service of country. ",
            "keyString": "150294s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is called the \"Lokhitwadi\"?",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Gopal Hari Deshmukh ",
            "optionC": "  Mahadev Govend Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  Mul Sankara ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Hari Deshmukh (18 February 1823 \u2013 9 October 1892) was an Indian activist, thinker, social reformer and writer from Maharashtra. His original surname was Shidhaye. Because of 'Vatan' (right of Tax collection) that the family had received,the family was later called Deshmukh. ",
            "keyString": "150540s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raja Rammohan Roy organised a historic agitation against the",
            "optionA": "  Caste system ",
            "optionB": "  Evil custom of sati ",
            "optionC": "  Degrading position of women in society ",
            "optionD": "  Practice of superfluous religious rituals ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRam Mohan Roy launched an attack on Sati that \"aroused such anger that for awhile his life was in danger\". ",
            "keyString": "150742s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What did Jyotiba Phule's Satyashodhak Samaj attempt in the last century?",
            "optionA": "  Saving the lower castes from hypocritical\nBrahmans and their opportunistic scriptures ",
            "optionB": "  Attacking the caste system ",
            "optionC": "  Led an antilandlord and antimahajan upsurge\nin Satara ",
            "optionD": "  Seperate representation for untouchables ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatya Shodhak Samaj was established by Jyotibha Phule in 1873. It was established with the aim of liberating the Shudras and backward Caste from the opposition of hypo critical Brahmans and their opportunistic scriptures. ",
            "keyString": "150923s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Arya Samaj Movement had been started by",
            "optionA": "  Swami Dayanand ",
            "optionB": "  Devendranath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "optionD": "  Keshub Chandra Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArya Samaj, (Sanskrit: \"Society of Nobles\") vigorous reform movement of modern Hinduism, founded in 1875 by Dayananda Sarasvati, whose aim was to reestablish the Vedas, the earliest Hindu scriptures, as revealed truth. ",
            "keyString": "151126s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy was the founder of",
            "optionA": "  Arya Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Ram Krishna Mission ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmo Samaj ",
            "optionD": "  Prathna Samaj ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaj Ram Mohan Roy founded Bramho Sabha in August 1828, it was later renamed as Brahmo Samaj. It aimed at purifying Hinduism and preaching 'monotheism' on the basis of reason and the Vedas and Upanishads. ",
            "keyString": "207020s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded the 'All India Harijan Samaj' in 1932?",
            "optionA": "  B R Ambedkar ",
            "optionB": "  Acharya Narendra Dev ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Jagjivan Ram ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarijan Sevak Sangh is a non-profit organisation founded by Mahatma Gandhi in 1932 to eradicate untouchability in India, working for Harijan or Dalit people and upliftment of scheduled castes of India. ",
            "keyString": "207686s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ a notable disciple of Sree Narayana Guru introduced Guru's visions and ideals to the western world",
            "optionA": "  Nataraja Guru ",
            "optionB": "  Kumaranasan ",
            "optionC": "  Chattambi Swamikal ",
            "optionD": "  K.Madhavan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNataraja Guru was a notable disciple of Sree Narayana Guru introduced Guru's visions and ideals to the western world. ",
            "keyString": "207914s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The founder of the 'Brahmo Samaj' was",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Swami Vivekananda ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Rammohan Roy founded brahmo samaj in Calcutta on 20 August 1828. It was more of a reformist movement of Hinduism which later got divided into adi brahmo samaj and sadharan brahmo samaj. Raja Ram Mohan Roy, one of the few 19th century reformers of Hindu society. ",
            "keyString": "208108s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the means adopted under Self Respect Movement?\nI. Violent protests against upper classes\nII. Undermine position of Brahmin priests by formalizing weddings without them\nIII. Boycott of temples and places of Brahmin residence",
            "optionA": "  I and III ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Only III ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe means adopted under Self Respect Movement was to undermine position of Brahmin priests by formalizing weddings without them. ",
            "keyString": "208303s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tipu was defeated in the __________ Anglo-Maratha war by the British",
            "optionA": "  First ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  Third ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British's diplomacy, conspiracy and intrigues against Tipu succeeded after the Third Anglo Mysore war which was ended by the Treaty of Srirangapatnam on March 22, 1792. ",
            "keyString": "266942s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the provision of the Treaty of Seringapatnam, signed between Tipu and Cornwallis \nI. Surrender of almost half of Tipu's territories, which were to be shared among the English, the Nizam and the Marathas.\nII.\u00a0Payment of a war indemnity of about Rs.3 crore by Tipu\nIII.\u00a0Stationing of British resident at Seringapatnam\nIV.\u00a0Sending two of his sons by Tipu as hostages to the British camp",
            "optionA": "  I & II ",
            "optionB": "  I, II & IV ",
            "optionC": "  I & III ",
            "optionD": "  I, III & IV ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe provision of the Treaty of Seringapatnam, signed between Tipu and Cornwallis were Surrender of almost half of Tipu's territories, which were to be shared among the English, the Nizam and the Marathas.\u00a0Stationing of British resident at Seringapatnam. ",
            "keyString": "267141s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The fourth __________War was of short duration and decisive and ended with Tipu's death on May 4, 1799",
            "optionA": "  Anglo-Mysore ",
            "optionB": "  French- Mysore War ",
            "optionC": "  Maratha -Mysore war ",
            "optionD": "  Nyzam-Mysore War ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Fourth Anglo\u2013Mysore War was a conflict in South India between the Kingdom of Mysore against the British East India Company and the Hyderabad Deccan in 1798\u201399. This was the final conflict of the four Anglo\u2013Mysore Wars. The British captured the capital of Mysore. The ruler Tipu Sultan was killed in the battle. ",
            "keyString": "267309s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shree Narayana Guru was a great socio-religious reformer of",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarayana Guru (ca. 1854 \u2013 20 September 1928), was a social reformer of India. He was born into a family of the Ezhava caste in an era when people from such communities, which were regarded as Avarna, faced much injustice in the caste-ridden society of Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "340501s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded the Sri Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam?",
            "optionA": "  Daya Nand Saraswati ",
            "optionB": "  Periyar Swami ",
            "optionC": "  Narayan Guru ",
            "optionD": "  Gopal Hari Deshmukh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana Yogam (SNDP) was founded in 1903 with the guidance and blessings of Sree Narayana Guru. ",
            "keyString": "341191s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the main inspiration for establishing Theosophical Society?",
            "optionA": "  Tackling zamindars issue ",
            "optionB": "  Women's education and their upliftment ",
            "optionC": "  Propagate Indian thought and culture there by revival of ancient religions of Hinduism, Zoroastrianism and Buddhism ",
            "optionD": "  Work for depressed classes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTheosophical society has played an important role in the history of the religion, society and culture of modern India. She and her associates advocated the revival and strengthening of the ancient religions of Hinduism, Zoroastrianism and Buddhism. They recognized the doctrine of the transmigration of the soul. ",
            "keyString": "341764s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote the book 'A Gift to monotheists'?",
            "optionA": "  David Hare ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionC": "  Mahadev Govind Ranade ",
            "optionD": "  Ramkrishna Bhandarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1809, Raja Ram Mohan Roy wrote 'Gift to Monotheists' in which he put forward the Idea that people must worship a single God. ",
            "keyString": "342295s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sri Narayana Guru was born into an __________ family.",
            "optionA": "  Ezhava ",
            "optionB": "  Nayar ",
            "optionC": "  Pulaya ",
            "optionD": "  Vannan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarayana Guru (ca. 1854 \u2013 20 September 1928), was a social reformer of India. He was born into a family of the Ezhava caste in an era when people from such communities, which were regarded as Avarna, faced much injustice in the caste-ridden society of Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "342779s50m51h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}